Morning, Jeff.
You're on mute.
How's that?
That's great. I think, is Raveen joining us as well?
I am-- He's, yeah, I think he's waiting to get in.
Okay. Right. We'll wait till he's in, and then we'll get ourselves underway. Okay.
Morning, Paul.
No, we don't have Raveen.
Sure.
I think. So nobody else is waiting?
No.
Jeff, Raveen's not waiting at the moment.
So-
They're saying that they can see you, but they have audio and video issues.
I think maybe they need to...
We have Shane Egan.
Yeah.
Will take us a moment to make sure we've got everybody online together.
Yeah, I'll just give you an answer for this one.
Okay. Yeah, sure.
Yes, now. Jeff, can you hear us?
Yes, I can.
I can.
Okay.
Good.
Just setting for video.
No, it's only until 9:00.
Go to full doc. Go to the...
Go to the business.
That one?
Yeah.
Right.
Okay, we can see you now.
Okay.
I think it's just me though.
Yeah, the same.
Yeah.
Maybe you should put it...
Yeah, obviously.
Zoom is a wonderful thing when it's working.
Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
Looks better. Nice to see you all there.
Good morning.
Look, welcome. Thank you very much for this time, and I know we had to move it from
last week because, I think it was illness and availability on your side.
But welcome. I hope everybody's feeling good now.
And I think this, really, where we kicked this off from was,
we've had the National Infrastructure Plan.
We've had the government's response to that.
Also, the opposition parties contributing to that, which is a good thing.
But then you, we take-- This is really is about the next steps from there, and I
think the opportunity for us to ask you some questions about where to from here,
operationalizing that plan, and yeah, delivering a
pipeline of infrastructure and delivering the right infrastructure in the right
way. So, do you want to kick off, Raveen and Jeff, with any comments you want to
make, and then we'll go to questions?
Not from me, Chair, because it's a very short one hour, so we'd rather use all the
time taking your questions.
Okay. And Jeff, you're fine as well?
Yeah, I'm fine with that. Yeah.
Okay. Well, look, colleagues, some questions. So who's going to kick us off? Tangy.
Thank you, Mr. Chair, and thank you all for joining us online.
I guess the first one is just a top high-level question, and that is obviously the
government have indicated their response to the plan.
You've heard from other parties as well.
What are some sort of top-level
reactions from the commission without delving into the specific detail?
I think that will come through in the course of the meeting.
Oh, yeah. Specific for the commission?
Yes, please.
Yeah. I think that there's probably-
Probably
... probably three that I would highlight.
The first is associated with recommendation two.
The minister has asked us to do some work looking at trying to better understand-
Mm-hmm
... the origin of cost escalation from the land transport sector.
Hang on, Jeff. Jeff, just hang on a moment.
We're getting a lot of feedback, I presume, between the two.
Yeah, course.
There's an echo going on there. Quite a big echo.
Someone needs to turn off their microphone.
Yeah, I think there's a microphone turn off, I think, maybe for all of you in at
the moment, and then we carry on. Sorry, Jeff.
Okay. Is that any better?
Yeah.
Yes.
It is. Okay.
Yeah. So point one is this work that we've been asked to now do associated with
recommendation two in the National Infrastructure Plan, which is decomposing
and understanding where the cost escalation in the land transport sector has come
from. We released a sort of preliminary findings, well, not preliminary
findings, but sort of casting a view over all of the work we've done looking at
costs and infrastructure yesterday, and that gives you a bit of a flavor for how we
are thinking about this one. But one of the main points from that was looking at
unit costs in land transport. We've seen those
at or a little bit higher than tripling over the last decade or two.
So there's a big question here about what is the origins of that.
In large part because these things are spilling over into other areas of Crown
investments. And, so that's why I think this has been a particularly large systemic
issue.
The second one would probably be
the recommendation there around assurance of both projects and the second
part of this, of asset management assurance as well.
The asset management assurance one really talks to the recommendations in the plan
around looking after existing assets and getting on top of renewal cycles and so
on. And the project-level assurance is very much about improving
the front end,
amongst other parts of planning for infrastructure, but getting a consistent
process for how we assess infrastructure projects, and that is the adaptation
of
gateway into the investment decision assurance program that the commission will be
establishing from November 1.
Thank you. Did you say there were three?
Yeah. Well, I was bundling asset management assurance and project-
Okay
... assurance, which, yeah. Yep. The asset management assurance being something
that is brand new, and we haven't done before.
So, that stands a little differently.
In terms of the asset management assurance, given that it's new, some of the other
stuff you have experience in either directly or through other kind of agencies such
as Treasury for the
sort of program assurance side of things, do you kind of foresee any
capability issues with the commission delving into those areas?
Or do you feel as though you're adequately resourced and understand what's required
in that space?
Well, what I would say is that currently, the first task for this actually
is getting in place a budget bid for it.
So we're not currently funded to do this, and we need to put forward a business
case with adequate funding to do that.
So the first part of your question is sort of, no, we need to get to the start line
on the funding and resourcing side of things.
It is a new function for central government.
There are other asset owners around New Zealand that do this as a matter of course,
and we have looked to them and their processes in trying to understand what the
resourcing looks like. But the magnitude of the task is
quite significant here, right? Because central government holds about 40% of all
assets in New Zealand. And so, there's quite a bit of work to
understand what this looks like and rightsize it
over time as well. I would also sort of bring in here, we've got Andy Hagen, who's
the GM of investment, who's running this program.
Andy, is there anything you would like to add to that?
Thanks, Jeff. Before I ask, can I just check that the sound's okay for the
committee?
Yeah. Your way it is. Whether it is when Jeff speaks again, we'll see.
But anyway, thanks.
We'll go back on mute when we-
Thanks
...
. I think to the member's question around capability, it's something that we are
thinking very carefully about. The commission's put quite a lot of effort into,
along with our colleagues across government, the treasury and the like, improving,
and bringing a focus to asset management over the last year.
And so, for example, we invested heavily in putting together some guidance for
agencies on asset management investment planning practices.
Obviously, as part of that, we needed to build our own capability,
to understand what good looks like and how that should play out in agency
land. But as Jeff's alluded to, we do think that there's a build process to go.
As part of the budget bid that Jeff's alluded to, we're thinking about options for
assurance, what that might look like.
There are, of course, all sorts of options around depth, expectations, frequency.
So we need to work through those things.
That obviously has flow-on applications for the resourcing expertise that we need
in-house.
Okay. Just one more.
One more. Okay.
I'll go to Simon and then Carlos. You've talked about central government.
Local government obviously have quite a role when it comes to infrastructure around
the country. What are the sort of next steps in terms of engagement with that
sector?
Yeah.
Well, what I would say is that one of the work programs we have moving forward is
to take our forward guidance, which we have for different asset classes, but has
been done more at a national level, and start to provide that more at a local
level. And we have always tried to draw a connection between the work of forward
guidance, signaling what we would expect to be spending in different sectors and
different regions, and start connecting that with spatial planning, as it's
imagined in the new resource management reform work.
And, so I think that that's a really important part of that in order to
lock down what is likely to be a fundable program of capital infrastructure at the
local level, rather than ending up in a similar place where we've been in the past
with projects that are ultimately affordable.
So I think that that's a really important part of the direction for local
government. I think the other sort of issue that I would flag that we have
had a lot of interactions with local government on is just the
sustainability of infrastructure investment, particularly with respect to growth
patterns in New Zealand. And, we've made this point to the committee before, that
we are
growing in ways that is ultimately making the financials much more
difficult for local government. And the significant challenge before us
is to start moving the ship on that one and growing in a way that's making
local governments financially stronger rather than financially weaker.
And that remains an issue that we think is really important to solve
if we're going to crack the infrastructure issue.
Actually, just on that, we've got Graeme Campbell, who's the Director of Economics
and Research at the commission, who's running both of these programs.
So I might just pause and see if there's anything he wants to add to that.
This is Graeme Campbell, Director of Economics and Research at the commission.
I'm sorry, we broke up there at the beginning, so we didn't quite hear the
question, although, I guess I'd say that Jeff's right, that we have a forward
work program to develop forward guidance at more at a regional level to help inform
long-run infrastructure planning and also
a research
agenda that includes further work in understanding how we can
improve financial sustainability for infrastructure at the local level.
So yeah, these are two issues that are on our agenda.
The other thing that I would just throw in there, of course, is the national
infrastructure pipeline as well, where we now have pretty good representation from
local government on their capital intentions plans.
And
for that work program, we want to get into a point where we're able to increasingly
reflect back good insights to local government so that they can see how their plans
look against other plans and help them use to sort of benchmark and right-size
those plans as well. So we see that as a significant tool that can be used in this
space also.
Thank you.
Okay, thanks. Simon.
Thank you. Good morning to the commission.
Just looking at your Making Every Dollar Count report, which is
heartening to hear that you're looking into this.
I see in, and I'm looking at page 42, over a
quarter of written assessment feedback cited the lack of low-cost options being
considered. Insufficient consideration of lower cost or non-built solutions to
infrastructure may be contributing to general cost growth over time.
What measures do you think the government should be considering to make sure that
the lowest cost and non-built solutions are considered first,
before additional scope or nice-to-haves are added?
Yeah. There's a couple of things in here.
First, I would say the
investment decision hierarchy is really important, and various agencies have this
kind of decision-making hierarchy, which starts with managing your existing assets,
utilization of those assets, demand management, really asking the question: Do we
need to build? And so I think that there's a part of this which is
about governance. There's a part of this which is about institutional culture
sometimes.
But I think simply asking these questions, what are the non-build options that we
have in front of us here, is really useful.
What we sort of talk to in that report is that as we've gone through and looked at
a lot of the projects that have come to us, we're looking specifically excuse
me, at the long-listing process down to the short-listing process.
And one of the metrics that we are looking at, usually that's done through a
multi-criteria analysis, right?
And how that process works is that a judgment will be made on
what sort of allocation out of 100% is given to various attributes
of the project. And one of the observations we've made is that cost is almost
always less than 50%. Now, when a
project is put forward in a cost-benefit analysis, that is
by definition 50%. You're dividing one over the other.
So what we sort of see here, the inference here, is that in the long-listing
process, we're using a methodology that is almost biasing itself towards the
higher cost options, and then we're using a methodology that more routinely, or
more appropriately, factors in cost.
And we're ending up with really expensive options at the back end.
And that is a comment we would make not of any one sector, but of a general
practice that we're seeing across infrastructure projects.
Thank you.
Thank you, Jeff.
There's lots of supplementary coming, just bear any answer you've got here.
But, Carlos.
Thank you.
Julia.
The commission report actually outline a suitable potential approach to funding New
Zealand future infrastructure needs.
How critical and scalable do you consider this funding mechanism to be in practice,
particularly given that the difference in political views or people expectation or
the skills of investment required and the long-term nature of the major
infrastructure projects?
Sorry, I missed the very first part of your question.
Were you talking about-
Yes
... a particular funding model?
No, we're just saying that in your report, the commission report, the National
Infrastructure Plan, you have mentioned that there's a suitable way to fund
infrastructure, including PPP, user-
Yeah
... user pay for work-
Right
... or funding from overseas. I just want to know that all this different kind of
funding mechanism, is it critical?
Or are we just trying to mention it for the sake of mentioning it in the report?
Yes. So one sort of minor correction there.
The PPP stuff and the sort of private capital, we would classify as a financing
mechanism, not as a funding tool, right?
Yes.
Funding tools, ultimately, we are thinking about taxpayers, ratepayers, and users.
Investment funds are not going to fund New Zealand's infrastructure.
We have to do that our ourselves.
Yes
Now, the plan really, I think one of the key observations of the plan is
that networked infrastructure should be able to sort of fund itself
off the network, and that it takes a sort of network users
approach to paying for infrastructure.
And the rationale for that is so that we can free up capital for
assets that are unable to do that because they don't necessarily have users, or
there's just a very narrow path to doing that.
And I'm thinking about things like schools and hospitals, and the defense estate,
and so on and so forth.
We are in a world where that delineation between those two things has very much
cracked, and we are starting to use consolidated revenues to fund networked
utilities, particularly in land transport, and so we're getting pressures on the
social infrastructure side. So the plan says as point one, to delineate between
those and get back to a funding mechanism, particularly in land transport, that has
the pricing tension within the network. That would be sort of point one.
Point two is, it really is talking more about why it's so
important for users to see the price of the service that they are
using. And this also is very important, right?
Because it allows asset owners to understand where they should be investing, right?
For instance, if a gate charge is really high at an airport, this is a signal
and a coordinating mechanism between the airline and the airport to consider
putting in another gate. If you don't have that pricing signal, and you don't have
the gate charge, and you fund it through a consolidated revenue, all of a sudden
the asset owner is in a position of having to really guess more at where the
additional capacity is needed. And we see sectors that are trying to do this
through consolidated revenues have a really tough time because they're simply not
getting good pricing information about where the demand is.
So as a result, I think the way that we price infrastructure is really
material to the problems that we perceive are out there.
And if we tend to reduce the user charge down to zero, as we do in, say,
water or land transport at times, then what we'll end up having is
overdemand, and we'll think we need to build more infrastructure.
But in fact, it's because we're not managing the demand effectively, and it gets
into a bit of a cycle. Yeah.
Callis.
Can I just use a potential second harbor crossing as an example?
I was going to...
What was the funding model or combination of funding model do you think would be
the most realistic for delivering a project of this size?
Well, the question that the commission asked at the outset of the work in the
National Infrastructure Plan was looking at how difficult this project is
to fund because of its size, right?
And because of its size, it means that we're often having to look at either
non-users within the network, which you're going to run into equity issues on, or
non-users from outside the network, which the equity issues will be even
harder. And so the question we asked is, well, given the capacity and
resilience issues of the need for a new investment,
how much would the users of that investment be prepared to pay given
the reduction in travel time and so on?
And this is sort of known as the revenue maximizing toll for
a new bridge, right? And the number that we had in the National Infrastructure Plan
was a $9 toll that would get you a number of somewhere between $7 and $9
billion, as a beginning scope for what a sort of
size of the project would look like, such that your users would
use it for the benefits that it provides.
So what we were trying to do there is sort of
reflect what a user perspective of project scope might look like.
The moment you go outside of that number,
you need to think about either asking non-users to pay, or as I say,
folks from outside the network, right?
And there are various ways that you could do that.
You can think about injections from consolidated revenue.
You can think about IFF, and so on and so forth.
But what stands as the issue to me is once you start doing that, you're getting
into a world of crowding out a lot of other needs that will also be in front of
you. And I think that that stands as one of the critical points to getting this
project across the line.
Yes, this is what the-
Sorry, what I'm going to do. I'm going to take Callis on this one, actually.
I think there's a few steps around this because I'm really interested in this issue
of funding for that network infrastructure, because there's been a few comments
being made recently, but that fly right in the face of that.
Oh, yeah. That was my question.
Yeah.
And this is why my supplementary go back to my primary question.
Like when you talk about now the user need to pay for it, or
people nowadays expect everything for free, how can we change people mindset or
expectation in order to implement or process the project?
How can you do that?
How do you change the mindset?
Yes, and people culture expectation.
Yeah. I mean, it is kind of interesting to me that the number we came up with,
particularly for this new crossing, was actually very similar,
ballpark the same as the inflation adjusted number from the toll that was
originally put across the harbor crossing when it started.
That is a sort of coincidence, and a lot of the media actually confused those two
things, but it happened to be that the number was the same.
I think part of this is a piece of advice that actually my
old professor told me in the world of infrastructure, is that once you've got a
toll in place, don't get rid of it. Don't get rid of it.
Because getting rid of a toll and then bringing it back is a very painful thing.
And there is the sense that we should get rid of the tolls once the debt is
paid back on the original capital project.
But of course, it has to get through a renewal cycle.
Capital projects depreciate.
And so in the first instance, the toll might serve as the way of paying back the
debt on the loan, but in the long run, the toll is essential to find your way
through a renewal cycle. Now, because we got rid of that toll many years ago, we're
in a position where we're struggling to get through a renewal cycle, and people
feel like the bridge is already paid for.
This is not what has happened with something like the Lower Thames Crossing, where
they too are trying to get through a renewal cycle, but they kept the toll, right?
And that has created the funding stream to see them through.
Part of this story is helping communities understand that their
assets depreciate, and they have to be renewed.
It is not just about funding the new capital expenditure.
And that is why we have talked so much about the need to fund 60 cents on the
dollar for renewals. It's not a small number. It's an enormous number.
It gets bigger as a country matures.
And actually, I think like the infrastructure conversation has matured along these
lines in the last couple of years, knowing what it takes to get through a renewal
cycle. So I know there's a lot of fanfare about the new shiny project, but actually
a big chunk of this is about how to get through a renewal cycle on the existing
bridge.
Thank you. Tracy, are you in the same space?
And Julianne, are you in the same space?
Yeah.
I think if we could deal with this particular issue around, a lot of it's around
transport funding renewals. And then Julianne, if you've got some other questions,
we'll go to those as well. I've got some of this here too. So Tracy.
Just a really quick add-on to that.
In terms of what sort of thoughts or mechanisms I'm thinking about how do we stop
that model disadvantaging small population
places where
the nationally significant infrastructure like South Island Freight, like what
tools, what mechanisms are within this to-
accountability.
Yeah. Well, as a general comment, I guess I would say that there is more
infrastructure in large places, right?
Infrastructure benefits from economies of scale.
That's why when you drive into Auckland CBD, you're going to see a concentration of
infrastructure. So clearly, as you sort of dissipate further away from the number
of funders you have, the options,
and what you can do,
are necessarily impacted. One part of this is
sound cost management,
and is understanding what you would need to see to believe that a project could
stack up in an area with not as many people.
In other words, what would be the sort of triggers you would be looking for?
At what size of a population could we think about new water storage or another
lane or another XXX? And I would look at that from the perspective of
enough people to fund the operating and maintenance costs on the
project, the
interest payments on the debt, and then inevitably the renewal cycle.
With freight in particular,
one of the challenge-- And I'll pass over to Graham.
I might just pause and wait, hand this one over to Graham in a second as well.
But one of the sort of interesting parts of freight networks is that they're
using oftentimes the same infrastructure that we're using for personal travel,
right? Like roads. And so they become a part of the demand stack of a road.
New Zealand is of a small enough nature and of a very
elongated nature that the case for sort of separating out freight
from passenger,
in many places in New Zealand, we just need to be a lot bigger before we could fund
ourselves through a renewal cycle on that quantum of infrastructure.
And that means oftentimes there's a sort of intermingling between these different
parts of the demand stack for freight.
But if you were to try and invest too much on one side or the other, you're going
to end up in the same world that we've talked about for many other sectors, which
is high capital stocks and not enough funders.
And then you're going to talk about maintenance issues, renewal problems.
When we have our natural hazard events, are we going to be able to build back and
so on? I'll just pause there because I know Graham Campbell also has been working
in this space as well. I don't know if there's anything you would like to add to
that, Graham.
Yes, Jeff. Just a short bit to add for that.
When we've been looking at thinking long term about the financial sustainability of
infrastructure, particularly in places where populations might not be able to
support it completely on itself, the recommendation in the National Infrastructure
Plan around for recommendation two for transport doesn't necessarily speak to every
piece of every kilometer of the road network or the transport network needs to pay
for itself. As Jeff mentioned, a couple of years ago, we put out a report which
looked at strong pricing principles across network infrastructure.
The first one of those was setting pricing so that you can recover costs, which is
what Jeff's been talking about. But another one of those important principles is
having a pricing scheme that where there are benefits to reaching scale on the
network, you might consider tweaks to your pricing methodology.
And what we observe across some other infrastructure networks, for example, in
electricity distribution transmission, is that not every bit of the network is
paying for each individual piece.
But because there are benefits to everybody being on the network at the same time,
some smaller population areas benefit from a sort of a cross-subsidy across the
network because there is that benefit of scale.
And so when we're thinking about
good, strong pricing principles that can
lead to quality infrastructure in those areas, which may not be able to support
them on their own, I think Jeff's got the right idea here that the question we
would be asking is, to what extent are there benefits of scale
to the network as a whole to justify sort of a different pricing approach for
that? And I think for a lot of our land transport network, that is kind of the case
where in areas which have lower population, we have built out a little bit
more developed transport network for the areas such as freight because there are
network benefits and benefits of scale.
Julian, did you have a question specifically in this area?
And then I'll have a couple more-
Yeah, actually, my question is pretty specifically in this area, and thanks very
much. Jeff, you mentioned that land transport, as a
network, ideally like water, you would be covering the cost of maintaining,
renewing, and enhancing by user charges.
I'm just wondering,
you've made the point on page eight of the plan that land transport funding system
is unsustainable. It's been receiving a huge amount of Crown loans and grants that
could have gone to other priority areas.
Is continuing to freeze fuel excise duty where it is and
borrow to cover the costs of the National Land Transport Fund in line with the
commission's recommendations and the National Infrastructure Plan, or is it going
in the opposite direction?
We would, of course, be looking at this over a longer time period, right, over a
30-year time period. And we have noted in the plan and other work as well that
there is a significant
gap between funding availability and capital investment intentions.
If it is the case that the-- And actually, I suppose one thing that I would add to
this, looking back over the last sort of 30 years of fuel excise
duty, it is true, of course, that we are down a lot from the peak.
Over a 30-year period, though, we are on average up about 12%, right?
And so there is always going to be what I would describe-
Sorry, Jeff.
Sorry.
Jeff, can you be clear, up 12% on what?
On the average over the last 30 years in
inflation-adjusted terms, right?
So we're way down if you just look over the last seven years, but if you look over
the last 30 years, we're not doing too badly.
The point I would sort of make in here is that
there is always pricing tension somewhere with an asset owner and a
user. And our job really is to assess, I think, where
a reasonable
place to land on a price is likely to be such that you don't have
contestability pushing it back down the other way.
And of course, this is determined by the value of the projects.
If people are seeing that projects are reducing their travel times by several
hours, you could expect prices to go up as a result, so they're happy to fund those
projects. But as the project quality narrows, you might actually start to see more
pricing tension come into it. With the forward guidance,
I think you can back out numbers associated with fuel excise
duty, and Graham, correct me if I'm wrong, but I think that those are somewhere
within the realm of five cents up to a little over twenty cents, I think is the
number over a 30-year period. So it's not nothing, and we're baking
in an increase in
prices there. But ultimately, what the plan is saying is that land
transport and demand for land transport are under increasing pressure from a few
things.
Changing demographics, we are getting older, and older people use transport
networks less, right? We're moving from a world of 5% annual average growth
rates several decades ago on our roading networks to numbers that are much closer
to zero to 1%, right? So there is quite a change in the profile of demand.
At the same time, what we're seeing is a real shift from new capital investment
to maintenance and renewals, partly
because that growth is slowing, and also I should say income growth as well, which
is a driver.
So we're sort of shifting more towards that.
But of course, the other thing in here is natural hazards, which essentially means
that our depreciation rates on a lot of our assets are higher, look like they're
probably going to be higher in the future than what they have been in the past.
And so that is going to start shifting more from new capital to
maintenance and renewals in the longer term.
So Graham, I don't know if you want to comment specifically on the
pricing assumptions and the forward guidance over the longer term.
Yeah, just briefly, what I'd say is that, just to echo what Jeff said, the
forecast and the forward guidance for land transport does take a longer-term view.
And you'll note in the forward guidance for land transport, the percentage of UDP
that we would sort of see as the affordable and sustainable level is lower than
what we have been spending over the last 20 years.
And so in some ways, the pricing tension that we're seeing right now, sort of the
desire to keep fuel excise duties and road user charges
flat or keep them where they are, is we think sort of a manifestation of what we've
sort of forecasted at a macro level.
Those slower population growth, slower income growth,
demand or vehicle kilometer travel growth slowing down a bit.
And so I guess we would sort of see this as a natural response to what the
dynamics and the forward guidance have.
The numbers that Jeff cited around what we would-- If you take the forward guidance
and you try to translate those to fuel excise duty and road user charges, the
forward guidance does not assume that fuel excise duties and road user charges will
be flat over the next 30 years, for two reasons.
One, the forward guidance is a long-term forecast, so it's very possible that over
windows of time, you would have investment below or above that, which would require
higher or lower fuel excise duties and road user charges.
And the second is those revenues fund not just capital
expenditure, but they also fund a lot of operational expenditure, so road safety,
maintenance of the road. So that's not CapEx per se.
We're talking sweeping things off the road.
But also public transport services are paid for by those revenue sources.
So our analysis needed to make sort of assumptions about that.
But the thrust of it is that the forward guidance doesn't assume flat road user
charges.
And a big chunk of the reason that is, is because even though we have those
headwinds from population growth and income growth slowing,
just generally construction prices tend to rise faster than the overall economy's
prices. And so, in order to sort of fund the investment that we think people will
demand, you will have to increase charges over time.
So-
But just speaking to this recommendation about the system returning to a model
where the cost of maintaining, renewing, and enhancing the existing network is
predominantly met by users.
If in the next three years or the next year or two,
governments are deciding, and parties in Parliament are deciding to continue to
increase the amount of general Crown funding that's going in to pay for the land
transport system, is that in line with the overall direction of returning to user
charges, or is it going in the opposite direction?
I would say, yeah, you're quite right.
The plan has said that a high-performing land transport network is one that
has a ring-fenced model of funding.
That is very much part and parcel of recommendation two.
If it's the case that FED is being kept lower and capital intentions remain the
same, then yes, it would push in that direction.
If there is a change to capital intentions that is commensurate to the reduction,
then it might go the other way. But-
So it's really the, whether or not Crown funding, general Crown
revenue is being used to pay for the land transport system or if, okay,
maybe we're not increasing revenue from users, but we're reducing spending in line
with that, then that's more in the direction of what you're recommending in the
National Infrastructure Plan.
I'd say that's a really good characterization. Yeah.
So can I just check, Jeff, you said 12%, so over the past 30 odd years, because
there was a stage where we had, before we got to the full hypothecation, where in
fact money was being taken from FED and RAC and being used for the General
Consolidated Fund. So the impression I've got is that in fact, transport was paying
for other stuff. Now we've reversed it and the Crown is paying for transport
things. But you're saying over the 30 years, if I understood you right, the 30
years passed, that we've had transport at least paying for itself.
But looking forward, that may well not be the case.
Well, it clearly isn't at the moment.
Yeah, it certainly hasn't been the last few years, and I think it's not projected
to be for the next few years as well.
So, but yeah, I'm certainly happy to send you the work that we've done
looking at how these prices have changed over the last 30 years, which has
motivated-
So this goes-- I'd be really interested in that because, I mean, obviously the
issue that Julianne has raised, one I was going to raise as well, which we've had
political parties sort of saying, well, we want the Crown to fund the gap
in transport funding for the next year or the next three years, depending on which
party it is. That does seem slightly antithetical to the direction that you're
encouraging us to take. But what you said earlier also was the tripling in cost
of delivery. Be really interested to hear a little bit more about that.
And we had a meeting with civil contractors the other day, and they said that,
because we talk about productivity, and they said that what we're now measuring,
they thought it was a pretty rough measure, rough reading measure, which is
basically how many kilometers did you deliver for how much money.
I'd be interested in what the measure is because they said what we're delivering
now in terms of the quality of roading compared to what we were delivering a while
back. All the consenting conditions, all the planting, the culverts, whatever else
it is that you're doing in a different way, that costs a heck of a lot more than--
They're actually not comparing like with like.
So I'd be interested in your comments around those areas.
Sure. So the work that we put out yesterday essentially tries to boil this down
into three areas, right? We're looking at input prices, we're looking at
productivity, which is how we convert those inputs into services, and then we're
looking at questions of scope on the project.
So with input prices, we're thinking about things like wages, labor.
We're thinking about concrete, structural steel, timber.
These are the sort of main inputs for
infrastructure projects. And we're looking at how our prices are benchmarked
against the range of other countries.
And the good news there is that we are essentially, with the exception of some
things that have to be sourced locally, like aggregates, we are essentially buying
in international prices, and we look more or less aligned on a lot of those things.
So when it comes to input prices, they don't seem to be able to do much explaining
as to why
we've got problems with
cost escalation.
Then when it comes to productivity, there's a bunch of stuff in here.
And everyone, I think kind of probably has their thing that they might point to,
whether it's procurement, governance, institutions,
or health and safety, all of these things that impact how we convert those inputs
into outputs. And what I would say with this kind of collection of things
is that generally they are slower moving.
They are controllable, but over a much longer time period, right?
I would hand the example of something like upzoning in urban areas, which we know
it makes it easier in many ways to deliver infrastructure because you've got more
funders around the same asset. But this has been a journey New Zealand has been on
since the amalgamation of Auckland Council in the 2010s.
So it's taken 15, 16 years, and you could make an argument that it's taken longer
than that as well. So slower moving, essential to move in a generally good
direction, but probably not going to get you quick wins.
When it comes to looking at productivity for civil construction,
one of the things we notice is that that civil construction particularly vis-à-vis
other kinds of construction, seems to have struggled, right?
It has gone backwards, whereas construction has gone forwards.
So this is an area where things seem to have got quite a bit harder in
recent times.
So it's an area that we always need to be thinking about.
The third area is scope, right? Which is how big is the project?
Are you thinking about one lane or two?
Are you thinking about 50,000 seats in the stadium or 30,000 seats and so on and so
forth.
And these are the areas where we have direct control over questions of
scope
almost all the time. So
we can impact these, and they have a big impact on the outturn cost at the end of
the day. When we look at the kind of drivers of scope, they are numerous and they
are many, right? There's a sort of consenting story to this.
There is a community expectation story.
But what I would say is that when it comes to public infrastructure,
the ability to confine scope is very, very challenging.
And we typically meet questions of, "Well, can we have this or can we have that?"
with bigger scope and bigger scope and bigger scope.
And that's fine, but at the end of the day, the question that we're asking is: How
does that impact on willingness to pay across all of the services that we need?
And if it ends up crowding out dollars in the wallet that are required for
wastewater treatment plants and other such things, that can create problems.
So we're essentially saying that it looks like of all of the rocks that you want to
turn over to understand why these costs are really increasing, questions of scope
loom large. And in the sectors that have strong regulation,
regulatory oversight, asking questions about, "Is the consumer willing to pay
for this asset, for the operation, maintenance, and renewal of this asset into the
future?" you tend to see
stronger control on scope.
Thanks. Tracey had a follow-up.
I did. And you said something at the start, which makes the supplementary
cogent, but then you went somewhere else. So bear with me.
Okay.
I just want to go back to the South Island.
Sure.
You talk about the fact that regional location of the infrastructure workforce as a
constraint, as a bit of a limits delivery.
So how does that play out geographically in particular, like that sequencing of
major projects? How do we know that that doesn't sort of hollow out the South
Island capability, particularly when it's married with the user pays
funding and is therefore, by definition, population-based?
Yeah. We did a little bit of work on this, excuse me,
in the sort of post-COVID world. And it was a bit of motivation, actually, for the
national infrastructure pipeline because we had a huge amount, an
enormous infrastructure spend in post-COVID years,
and it really created a sort of inflationary environment
for competition over people and resources.
And you'd have people going out to market at the same time for the same thing,
competing from a
market which wasn't able to scale really fast, right?
And so this sort of coordination, particularly for central government as the
biggest investor out there, as I say, not everything, but 40%,
can be decisive in what the outturn costs you're going to pay when you're really
pushing against those capacity constraints.
And I would say every country sort of struggles with this.
Like a big project in New Zealand might be a few billion dollars, but
something like the suburban rail loop in Melbourne is probably a similar story.
If you go and have a look at the big projects in Saudi Arabia, they're doing
exactly the same thing, but on a global scale, right?
They're pulling in all of the engineers from around Europe and having a similar
impact. So in large part, this was one of
the motivations for pulling together the national infrastructure pipeline, and then
being able to show on a regional level, are you way outside of local domestic
capacity constraints, or can we see a path through this?
The last example I would give would be Cyclone Gabrielle, where the pipeline was
used to show likelihood of
building back over certain time scales.
Originally, of course, when there's a big disaster, you want to build back really
fast. But this was in a location where they didn't have very deep labor markets,
and there was a lot of work to do. And when we looked at the sort of projections,
it created this enormous bulge. You looked at it and you're like, "Well, that's not
going to happen." Not without extreme cost increases to incentivize people to all
locate, and even then you would have problems with housing and downstream
infrastructure effects. So these capacity constraints are really going to be
decisive in what timescale is actually possible for a
country of our size to deliver to some of these things, and it depends on a lot of
the size of the projects. But in short, the answer to that question is you've got
to have a good sense of looking around what else is on the books to make sure that
you're not going to run into these big cost increases along the way.
Jeff, just on that issue of pipeline, again, it was an issue raised by civil
contracts tonight. It's an issue which has also been one that our political parties
raise on a regular basis, not looking at anybody in particular.
The
pipeline and the actual doing, delivering the pipeline.
So we've got a pipeline of intention, but actually delivering on that pipeline is
particularly in the asset management side of things.
What role can the Infrastructure Commission play in saying, "Hey, look you said
Council X, Council Y, Ministry X, Ministry Y," whoever it is, "You said you were
going to planning on building this pipeline.
Are you actually doing it as opposed to not doing it?" Because, of course, if we're
trying to do this to
help the construction and jobs and so on, and the investment in
the construction equipment, it actually helps if the pipeline's
actually roughly helped it.
Yes. Well, look, what I would say here is that the biggest gain to
be had here is through those contracts which are regular,
uncontroversial, and we know that we're going to need them-
Execution
... under a range of scenarios, right?
And this is all pointing towards maintenance and renewals.
This is the meat and potatoes of,
well, needs to be the meat and potatoes of any sort of firm in the market out
there.
But when it comes to new capital investments,
I guess what I would say here is that these things are inherently uncertain in
many ways. Now, I'm not saying we can't get better at signaling within time regions
when they might be needed, and think about it more as a timing analysis and what we
would need to see to believe. That kind of certainty, I think we should be able to
give the market, right? We will increase the capacity on this road from 2:00 to
4:00 when we see the number of vehicles going from 20,000 to 40,000, or something
like that. And then it's a question of, well, what do the growth paths look like
and when will that occur? That kind of certainty, to my mind, it would be the sign
of a more sophisticated asset owner and would be a good thing to do.
But in this world of saying, "Well, we're going to do this project in 2032, forget
everything else that we see around us," that is not a sophisticated asset owner in
operation, right? Because an asset owner knows that they might not build it if they
don't see the people around them. And if they choose to build it simply out of
certainty, they're going to run into financial distress when they don't have the
money to maintain and operate the thing.
So I actually think there's a bit of a two-way conversation here that we need
between government asset owners and
the industry to understand what situation we're in when it comes to our assets.
Yeah, I was talking more about the meat and potatoes part, but-
Yeah, well-
... that was time separate. I'll take one last question from Carlos, and then we're
going to have to wrap up time-wise.
We just want to check, because we've got a high demand on infrastructure.
How can we ensure that public funding is focused on delivering essential
infrastructure rather than spending or being absorbed by expensive design features
or on essential architectural elements?
For example, CRL have been mentioned that the cost can be half the cost if we
decide to use a more industrial design.
How can we make sure the taxpayer funding can be better used?
Half the cost
What was mentioned by the former CRL chief executive form.
Sweetie, but just saying it could have been a couple billion less.
Half a billion, that's not half the cost.
I just said a lot more than that. Yeah, carry on.
Yes. But I think-
I mean, I think-
... something we hear.
Yeah. I honestly think that the rock you would want to turn over here is what I
alluded to last time, which is scope and how scope is allowed to move and
shift across time. We have often made this point
that of all of the capital investments that came up for funding over the last
five years,
somewhere between 35% and 50% of those have adequate business casing.
Right? This is a number that is not high enough.
So I think doing this kind of early work to understand
questions of scope, but also affordability, it's easy to
add scope to it and then push a funding problem to a decision-maker. Right?
We came up with this big project, it's on you to fund it now.
And the decision-makers are looking around at all of the other assets that they
need to maintain it, but also invest in, and they're going, 'You've given me a
number that has created these enormous trade-offs with all of these other services
that we need.' The National Infrastructure Plan point blank says we need to
start with a level of affordability that is sustainable.
That is what we have done with something like the Harbor Crossing.
We started there rather than finished there,
in order to motivate the kind of scope that is going to get you to a point where a
decision-maker can sign on the dotted line. Right?
So having control over that scope, making sure it's going through the right
processes with the right business casing.
I would also say bringing a lot of this stuff in-house is essential
for central government over a longer time period. Right?
If you outsource the thinking and the scoping of the project, it can ultimately
result in a scope that you can't fund.
Right? So, building the capability to ask these questions internally stands as a
big issue as well. I'll just quickly pause and see if any of the others want to add
anything to that, Ravin or otherwise.
Thanks, Jeff. No, I think you've covered it well. It is the scope.
Even the CRL example is scope. So...
Yeah.
Let's just... Okay, look, unfortunately, there's plenty more questions we could
ask, but we are going to have to call it there because we've got to move on to the
next. Really appreciate the work you do, really appreciate the time you've given
us, and I'm sure there are other things we'd like to follow up on some of those
things with a lot of wisdom in what you're saying, so really appreciate it.
Thank you.
Great.
Thank you, Mr. Chair.
Thank you.
Thank you. Have a great day.
Okay, thank you.
Thank you. Have a good day.